<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Ciaran McNulty]]></title>
    <link href="/blog/tags/hardware.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-05T12:56:28+01:00</updated>
    <id>/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[A great customer service experience from Amazon]]></title>
            <link href="/a-great-customer-service-experience-from-amazon"/>
            <updated>2011-07-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
            <id>/a-great-customer-service-experience-from-amazon</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I got a Kindle around the start of the year, and I guess it's something I could write about separately but I'm fairly sure it's the device I've had that I've got the best entertainment value out of in terms of cost per pound.</p>

<p>If you've seen the ads, you'll come away with the impression that the Kindle can be <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uLg817U9URM">shoved in a draw, licked by a dog</a> and generally thrown around the place so that's how I treated mine.</p>

<p>Last week I was talking about the Kindle to some workmates and really praised its rugged form and overall resilience - in retrospect it was asking for trouble. The very next morning I took it out of my bag and saw it looking like this:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ciaranmcnulty/5904816848/" title="Broken Kindle by CiaranJMcNulty, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6011/5904816848_b99d43a2b7.jpg" width="374" height="500" alt="Broken Kindle"></a></p>

<p>My heart sank - what were the odds that Amazon would be able to honour that as a repair? It's fairly clear that it's been knocked around in my bag or something and the screen has failed.</p>

<p>I thought I'd give it a punt anyway and rang Kindle Support. My first experience was not good - the lady on the other end of the line seemed to have trouble understanding me, and took me through a fairly silly 'turn it off and on again' routine. I then got put on hold for a few minutes during which I made <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/CiaranMcNulty/status/88166417123385344">this angry tweet</a>.</p>

<p>However as soon as I got put through to second line support, the whole process was a revelation! Even though I was honest about not having a case and the fact it was clearly damaged from being in my bag, Amazon are sending me a new Kindle immediately which will be here Thursday, after which I have to return the broken one in the box provided.</p>

<p>I felt a bit embarrassed about the tweet so <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/CiaranMcNulty/status/88167696931364865">tried to correct it</a>.</p>


<p>What other hardware companies are this accommodating? Not many I'd warrant so a big thumbs up to Amazon from me. </p>

<p>(Just hope they launch library lending soon in the UK!)</p>]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>