<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Ciaran McNulty]]></title>
    <link href="/blog/tags/javascript.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-05T13:44:14+01:00</updated>
    <id>/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Zend Framework bindings for Frontal]]></title>
            <link href="/zend-framework-bindings-for-frontal"/>
            <updated>2010-04-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
            <id>/zend-framework-bindings-for-frontal</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Having thought further about <a href="/source/blog/2010/03/frontal-a-new-approach-to-triggering-javascript-behaviour">Frontal, Carl's JS library</a>, I wrote a quick View Helper to make it easier to use it in Zend Framework projects.</p>

<p>It's <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/1845336/Frontal-ZF.tar.gz">available to download</a> on Dropbox, it's available under the MIT licence.  I'll bung it up on somewhere like GitHub once I work out how Git works.</p>

<h4>Basic usage</h4>

<p>Before you do anything you'll need to register the helpers in your <tt>application.ini</tt>:</p>

<code><pre>
resources.view.helperPath.Frn_View_Helper = /path/to/Frn/View/Helper
</pre></code>

<p>to get it to output anything you'll need to echo the frontal helper at the bottom of the page:</p>

<code><pre>
...
&lt;?= $this->frontal() ?&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
</pre></code>

<p>By default this will echo nothing! Don't panic, it'll start doing things once you've loaded some stuff into it.  The main use-case here is that you're echoing the helper out in some sort of template (Zend_Layout particularly) but pushing configuration into it from your individual views.</p>

<p>Firstly, you can override the path Frontal will use, for instance if there's a page appears under lots of different URLs but you just want one rule that matches it against '/foo':</p>

<code><pre>
&lt;? $this->frontal->location('/foo'); ?&gt;

will output:

&lt;script&gt;
$frn.location('/foo');
&lt;/script&gt;
</pre></code>

<p>Secondly, you can provide some data that frontal might find useful (rather than dump it in global scope).  The data is auto-converted to JSON so it's a fairly nice way of feeding data from PHP to JS:</p>

<code><pre>
&lt;? $this->frontal->data(array('foo', 'bar')); ?&gt;

will output:

&lt;script&gt;
$frn.data(["foo","bar"]);
&lt;/script&gt;
</pre></code>

<p>That's pretty much it for now, but it works pretty well and I'm going to be building it into a work project.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Frontal - a new approach to triggering Javascript behaviour]]></title>
            <link href="/frontal-a-new-approach-to-triggering-javascript-behaviour"/>
            <updated>2010-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/frontal-a-new-approach-to-triggering-javascript-behaviour</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My friend <a href="http://sweetnr.com">Carl</a> has just released <a href="http://sweetnr.com/70">a really interesting Javascript library called Frontal</a>.  I've had a night to sleep on it and thought I'd share my thoughts.</p>

<p>The key problem Frontal addresses is <em>'some Javascript needs to be run only on some pages'</em>.  There are a few different approaches to this:</p>

<h4>Per-page scripts</h4>

<p>The first approach is to have lots of Javascripts that only apply for the current page, and insert them in the HEAD of the document:</p>

<code><pre>
&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;script src="base.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;script src="something-page-specific.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
</pre></code>

<p>Pros:</p>
<ul>
<li>You can attach your scripts modularly</li>
<li>No inline scripts</li>
</ul>

<p>Cons:</p>
<ul>
<li>Lots of JS files to keep track of</li>
<li>Lots of HTTP requests to your server</li>
<li>Each page's JS isn't precached</li>
<li>No way of passing parameters to the script, everything has to be hard-coded</li>
</ul>

<h4>Inline triggers</h4>

<p>A second approach is to have some base library but then activate with some inline script in your page:</p>

<code><pre>
&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;script src="base.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  [...]
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
  [...]
  &lt;script&gt;
    doSomeBehaviour('foo', 'bar');
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
</pre></code>

<p>Pros:</p>
<ul>
<li>One JS that's easily cached</li>
<li>Triggered functionality per-page</li>
</ul>

<p>Cons:</p>
<ul>
<li>Mixes JS with HTML</li>
</ul>

<h4>POSH triggering</h4>

<p>This third approach is one I've preferred to use in the past is to have the Javascript pick up elements that exist in the markup in some sort of <a href="http://microformats.org/wiki/posh">POSH</a> form.</p>

<code><pre>
&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;script src="base.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  [...]
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
  [...]
  &lt;div id="foo"&gt;
    &lt;span class="bar"&gt;An element&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
</pre></code>

In this instance the base.js would pick up that there's an element with @id="foo" and do some action based on it (or rather, attach some behaviour).

<p>Pros:</p>
<ul>
<li>One JS that's easily cached</li>
<li>JS only applies when needed</li>
</ul>

<p>Cons:</p>
<ul>
<li>Lots of findById() to check every possible element that might trigger a behaviour</li>
<li>Can only apply after DOM is ready</li>
</ul>

<h4>The Frontal approach - path-based actions</h4>

<p>What frontal does quite simply and brilliantly is allow you to specify Javascript that gets run based on the URL of the current script:</p>

<code><pre>
$frn('/blog', function(){
   // some blog-specific action
});

$frn('/news/latest', function(){
   // e.g. script that refreshes the list of news items
});

$frn(/blog\/.*zend.*/, function(){
   // action for blog items with Zend in the URL
});
</pre></code>

I find this approach really interesting, and would be pretty keen to see how it can be integrated with your average framework's routing mechanism (specifically ZF and the URL view helper).

<p>Pros:</p>
<ul>
<li>One big JS</li>
<li>JS only applied on pages where it's needed</li>
</ul>

<p>Cons:</p>
<ul>
<li>Page-specific JS might not be fine-grained enough</li>
<li>Need to link to Frontal as a library to use (unless you replicate the pattern)</li>
</ul>

<h4>Looking forward</h4>

<p>At first glance I tend to think that a mixed strategy of the Frontal and POSH approaches - I still tend to think that JS should get as much of the 'stuff' it needs to understand from POSH-esque structures within the page (e.g. a Google Map probably shouldn't have it's coordinates hardcoded in the JS). However it does get costly to keep traversing the DOM, and you can't always wait for the DOM to be available, so there's a strong argument for combining that with Frontal and nesting the POSH checking inside Frontal clauses.</p>

<p>I'm going to keep nagging Carl about getting this integrated into a Zend project, and would like to see it bundled into a jQuery plugin.</p>

]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clarifying Javascript-PHP communication using JSON-RPC]]></title>
            <link href="/clarifying-javascript-php-communication-using-json-rpc"/>
            <updated>2010-03-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/clarifying-javascript-php-communication-using-json-rpc</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I think of myself first and foremost as a PHP developer but serious sites are getting more and more JS-heavy as time goes on so it gets harder (and less pragmatic) to try and avoid dealing with JS<->PHP communication of some sort.</p>

<p>I'm a big advocate of RESTful design so tend to end up attempting to write scripts that do lots of GETs and POSTs (as appropriate) and parsing out whatever custom response format I've decided JSON requests will return.  It feels good - like I'm sticking to my principles and 'doing it right' but it's a long painful slog that can feel like self-flagellation at times.</p>

<p>It's also slow and hard to prototype - it's hard to argue in favour of some abstract design idea when it's making you take forever to generate simple tasks .  Sometimes when I feel lazy what I really want is a way of calling my PHP objects directly from the JS and not worrying about what's happening in the underlying HTTP, and that's what <a href="http://json-rpc.org">JSON-RPC</a> provides.</p>

<p>In this blog I'll be showing some simple examples of JSON-RPC in action but first let's look at the pros and cons.</p>

<h4>Why JSON-RPC is awesome:</h4>

<ul>
<li>It includes basic error handling as part of the protocol</li>
<li>It hides away all the client-server communications from me the developer</li>
<li>It looks a bit like SOAP so is fairly familiar</li>
<li>I don't have to spend time writing RESTful response formats and pondering URLs to get working code</li>
</ul>

<h4>Why JSON-RPC sucks:</h4>

<ul>
<li>It's not <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rest">REST</a>ful - requests from the client come in as POSTs to on URL without a clear semantic 'resource' behind it</li>
<li>There may be specifics to the HTTP that aren't covered by the abstraction</li>
</ul>

<p>I suspect a lot of developers reading the lists above will be thinking "hell yeah, sounds good, how can I have it?"</p>

<h4>The protocol</h4>

<p>I won't go into all the ins and outs of the protocol but it's worth taking a quick look.  The basic paradigm is that the server has a bunch of methods that can be called by the client, that take different parameters.</p>

<p>An example request is a POST to the server that looks like this:</p>

<p><tt>{ "method": "greet", "params": ["Ciaran"], "id": 1234 }</tt></p>

<p>This is the PHP equivalent of $server->greet("Ciaran").  The ID parameter is used to match up requests and responses.  The response would look like this:</p>

<p><tt>{ "result": "Hello Ciaran", "error": null, "id": 1234 }</tt></p>

<p>So the result is a string literal with no error conditions - there's not much more to it than that to be honest, aside from error handling.</p>

<p>It would be fairly simple to implement either side of the protocol yourself on a project, but the real strength is of course that once something is a standard, the rest of the world goes to work on it and starts writing up libraries that lazy programmers like us can use! Let's take a look at two libraries, a Zend Framework one on the PHP end and a jQuery one on the Javascript end.</p>

<h4>JSON-RPC in PHP: Zend_Json_Server</h4>

<p><a href="http://framework.zend.com/manual/en/zend.json.server.html">Zend_Json_Server</a> is pretty simple to use, you will need a class that exposes and handles the methods you're going to be using that's properly docblock commented (this is used by the component to see the parameter and return types):</p>

<code><pre>class My_Service_Handler
{
    /**
    * @param string $name
    * @return string
    */
    public function greet($name)
    {
        return "Hello $name";
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>You can then proxy JSON-RPC requests along into this object using the Zend Framework component, Zend_Json_Server:</p>

<code><pre>
$server = new Zend_Json_Server();
$server->setClass('My_Service_Handler');
$server->handle();
</pre></code>

<p>Now any requests like our examples above will get an appropriate response.  Again fairly straightforward stuff I think, and should be familiar to anyone who's used a SOAP server in PHP.  All of the complexity of decoding the response and encoding the request is handled by the component.</p>

<h4>JSON-RPC in JQuery: zendjsonrpc</h4>

<p>There are a huge number of jQuery plugins to do JSON-RPC, but <a href="http://plugins.jquery.com/project/zendjsonrpc">this one is specifically written to work with the Zend_Json_Server</a> so I figured it's as good an example as any.  If you look at the source code of the plugin it's fairly straightforward and I'm sure it'd be easy to write your own if you preferred.  The basic usage is:</p>

<code><pre>
var client = jQuery.Zend.jsonrpc({url: '/path/to/service/handler.php'});
var message = client.greet("Ciaran");
alert(message);
</pre></code>

<p>As you can see, once the client object is constructed with the service URL you as a developer have a local JS object that exposes the exact same methods the My_Service_Handler has.</p>

<h4>Overall</h4>

<p>What I really find attractive about the JSON-RPC protocol is that, well, someone else has implemented it for me in the two components above.  That means that I can stop worrying about AJAX and start pretending that my PHP object is somehow present locally in my JS and that I can just call its methods at will.</p>

<p>That's a really powerful abstraction. No doubt like most abstractions there are places where it leaks around the edges but the simplicity of the idea and the clarity it brings to JS<->PHP communication make it an approach I'll be certainly investigating for my next JS-heavy project.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Keeping your Javascript clean]]></title>
            <link href="/keeping-your-javascript-clean"/>
            <updated>2008-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/keeping-your-javascript-clean</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been doing a bit more Javascript recently, specifically using Prototype AJAX stuff with Google Maps ,and I've come up with a few guiding principles that have helped me keep stuff neat and tidy.  I thought I'd share them with you, my handful of readers.</p>

<h4>SCRIPT tags should live inside HEAD</h4>

<p>There are very few reasons for having SCRIPT tags inside the document body.   The main one, use of <tt>document.write()</tt> nearly always leads to ugly code.  It's also not actually allowed in XHTML, despite most browsers accepting it as long as the page is delivered as <tt>text/html</tt>.</p>

<p>Furthermore, SCRIPT in the document body is in my opinion always the result of a perceived problem that's actually the result of poor architectural choices.</p>

<h4>Data and markup should live in HTML and styles should live in CSS</h4>

<p>Somewhat related to the first point, sometimes it's tempting to do something like this on-page or in some server-generated JS to get information into your scripting language:</p>

<code><pre>
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
lng = &lt;?php echo $lat ?&gt;;
lat = &lt;?php echo $lng ?&gt;;
drawTheMap(lat,lng);
&lt;/script&gt;</pre></code>

<p>What's a little nicer is to put the info somewhere into your HTML with a distinct ID or CLASS, and let your scripting language read it out of the DOM.  That way you can avoid the sticky situations of trying to generate client-side code from your server-side code.</p>

<p>For example the data could be stored on the page somewhere sensible using <a href="http://www.microformats.org/wiki/geo">the GEO microformat</a>:</p>

<code><pre>
Location: &lt;abbr id=&quot;location&quot; class=&quot;geo&quot; 
    title=&quot;&lt;?php echo $lat ?&gt;;&lt;?php echo $lng ?&gt;&quot;&gt;
    6 Example Street
&lt;/abbr&gt;</pre></code>

<p>And then read out from the DOM using something like the following:</p>

<code><pre>
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
if(locElement = document.getElementById('location')){
    if(locElement.className='geo'){
        if((loc = locElement.title.split(';')) &amp;&amp; loc.length==2){
            lng = loc[0];
            lat = loc[1];
            drawTheMap(lat,lng);
        }
    }
}
&lt;/script&gt;</pre></code>

<p>Now, that looks slightly longer than the previous example but consider that it won't change from page to page, so can live in a client-cached JS file.  The first example would need to either lie inside every HTML page, or be in a server-generated .js with nocache headers and be reloaded on every page.</p>

<p>As an aside, if you really don't have anywhere sensible in your visible markup to show this data, you could always put it in a HEAD element like META if you really need to - I've toyed with keeping my google API keys in there for instance.</p>

<h4>There should only be one SCRIPT tag on the page</h4>

<p>Perhaps the rule I'm least sure of, but one I've been trying to stick to as much as possible and I've found it helpful.  Having one central JS that controls everything makes the path of execution of your code a lot cleaner.  When you have multiple SCRIPTs on the page (and when you have them knocking around in the BODY) you can get into situations where different scripts are trying to set window.onload, executing out of order and so forth.</p>

<p>To continue the Mapping example above, a lot of my pages used to have:</p>

<code><pre>
&lt;script language=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;myscript.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;?php if(thereMightBeAMapOnThisPage()){ ?&gt;
&lt;script language=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;http://maps.google.com...&quot;&gt;
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;?php } ?&gt;</pre></code>

<p>This relies on the script generating the head knowing whether the mapping API is needed.  Neater in my opinion is to eliminate this and detect inside my own Javascript, whether the API is needed:</p>

<code><pre>
&lt;script language=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;

if(locElement = document.getElementById('location')){
  var script = document.createElement(&quot;script&quot;);
  script.src = &quot;http://www.google.com/jsapi?key=asd[...]asd3&amp;
  script.type = &quot;text/javascript&quot;;
  document.getElementsByTagName(&quot;head&quot;)[0].appendChild(script);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</pre></code>

<p>What this is doing essentially is inserting the SCRIPT into the HEAD via the DOM!  It may well look messy at first glance, but it's worked in all the browsers I've tried it on and is the way Google recommend pulling in their external scripts.</p>

<h4>Use the Google AJAX Libraries API</h4>

<p>OK so this isn't so much a rule as something I think is fairly handy, and I'm sorry if I keep going on about Google!</p>

<p><a href="http://code.google.com/apis/ajaxlibs/">Google are hosting lots of the common Javascript libraries</a>, including Prototype which I use.  Loading your Javascript library via the AJAX loader doesn't make much difference, but it does offer a few advantages:</p>

<ul>
    <li>You get to use the google.load() functionality from within your script, which is quite tidy and helps with my previous point.</li>
    <li>It's served from the Google servers so you don't pay for the bandwidth, and it can download faster in parallel with content from your domain (most browsers won't open more than 2 simultaneous connections to a single server).</li>
    <li>Because it's sitting at one central location, if everyone starts doing this then most clients will have the JS already cached when they hit your site, rather than them redundantly loading it for each server they encounter.</li>

    <li>If you do decide in future that Google are too evil to download code from, switching back to a local copy of your library is fairly trivial.</li>
</ul>]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>