<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Ciaran McNulty]]></title>
    <link href="/blog/tags/writing.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-05T12:56:28+01:00</updated>
    <id>/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Doctrine article in php|architect]]></title>
            <link href="/doctrine-article-in-php-architect"/>
            <updated>2009-08-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
            <id>/doctrine-article-in-php-architect</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ah, fame at last!</p>
<div>
 <div class="figure narrow">
    <a href="http://phparch.com/c/phpa/magazine/index"><img src="http://static.phparch.com/common/issues/small/0104.jpg" width="200" height="258" alt="Cover of php|architect"/></a>
    <p class="caption">The latest issue</p>
</div>

<p>It looks like <a href="http://phparch.com/c/phpa/magazine/index">the new issue of php|architect</a> is out, and contains my article about <a href="http://www.doctrine-project.org/documentation">Doctrine</a>, the PHP-based Object Relational Mapper.</p>

<p>It feels like ages since I wrote it (I'm no longer a 'freelance PHP developer' for a start) so re-reading it was actually a slightly weird experience.</p>
</div>
<p>It's my first published work, and I'm fairly happy with it.  Hopefully I'll get another chance to write for php|architect, I just need to think of another subject that I have something to say about.</p>

<p>The bad news for most of you cheapskates is that php|architect is a subscription-only publication so you can't read my article for free!  However, I would genuinely recommend the magazine, especially as it's only effectively $2.50/issue.  Obviously I wouldn't recommend it for people who aren't interested in PHP, however!</p>]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Article in php|architect (maybe)]]></title>
            <link href="/article-in-php-architect-maybe"/>
            <updated>2009-05-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
            <id>/article-in-php-architect-maybe</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sorry for the lack of recent posts - I've been distracted recently working on an article I've written for <a href="http://www.phparch.com/">php|architect</a>.</p>

<p>In theory it'll be in the August issue but these things are subject to change and frankly they could probably still reject it if they wanted to.</p>

<p>Anyway there's still time to subscribe if you want to get a copy!</p>]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>